<article>
  <h1>Machine Learning Basics</h1>
  <summary>
    Learn some core concepts and lingo in this tutorial,
    by training software to prescribe contact lenses.
  </summary>
  <section>
    <h2>
      So, what is machine learning?
    </h2>
    <p>
      It's all about teaching computers to see patterns in data.
      We see patterns in data all the time. If I show you a picture of a blimp,
      you'll recognize it as a blimp because you've seen blimps in the past and 
      you've learned that blimps are large, egg-shaped flying machines.
    </p>
    <p>
      Well, computers have none of this intelligence built-in. Machine learning is
      all about training software to see data as blimps, cars, people, spoken words,
      stock prices, and almost anything else you can think of.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      The Task
    </h2>
    <p>
      The machine learning task is this: we have <em>training data</em>, which are examples
      of different classes we want to teach the computer about. We want to train a <em>classifier</em>
      to label new examples with the correct class, by showing it the training examples.
    </p>
    <p>
      Alright, let's get our hands dirty and start using ProtoM on a real example:
      deciding what kind of contact lenses a person needs. On the right, you should
      be in the <em>Data</em> tab. From the <em>Choose data</em> menu, select <em>contact-lenses</em>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Take a moment to look at the examples in the contact-lenses dataset. Here, we have 24 examples of 
      people and 3 classes of contact lens prescriptions: <em>soft</em>, <em>hard</em>, and <em>none</em>.
      The histogram shows how many examples are in each class. If you click on a class in the histogram,
      the examples from that class will be listed below.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Features
    </h2>
    <p>
      How do we train the classifier? Each example in the training data is actually a set of
      <em>features</em> that describe the example, and distinguish it from examples in other
      classes.
    </p>
    <p>
      Take for instance <em>Example 2</em>, a person who needs <em>soft</em> lenses. She is young,
      has a myope prescription, doesn't have astigmatism and has a normal tear production rate.
      These features hopefully correlate in some way to what kind of contact lenses are 
      needed for each individual.
    </p>
    <p>
      During training, it is the classifier's job to learn this correlation. That way, when
      a new person comes into the optometrist's office, the classifier can decide what kind
      of contact lenses they need based on their age and vision conditions.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Classifiers
    </h2>
    <p>
      In order to train the classifier, we must choose one first. Click on the <em>Classifier</em>
      tab at the top of the page. From the <em>Choose classifier</em> menu, select
      <em>trees.J48</em>.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is a type of classifier called a decision tree, which learns a set of rules for 
      classifying examples based on feature values. How the tree works is outside the scope
      of this tutorial, but you can find a good description
      <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_tree" target="_blank">here</a>.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Training and Testing
    </h2>
    <p>
      It's time to train the classifier. Click the <em>Training and Testing</em> tab. Click 
      <em>RUN</em>. Along with a summary of the trial's training data, features and classifier,
      <em>results</em> for this trial should appear on the page. For example, the accuracy
      is something like 83%.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Results
    </h2>
    <p>
      What do the results mean? How have we checked that the classifier worked? This is done 
      using <em>cross-validation</em>. The idea is to use 9/10 of the data for training, and the
      other 1/10 for testing. This is repeated 10 times (for each 'fold') and the results from
      each train-and-test are added up.
    </p>
    <p>
      The result is that each example is given to the decision tree at some point for classification.
      If the actual label doesn't match the classifier's decision, this is counted as an error.
      The accuracy means that 83% of the people were given the correct type of contact lenses.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Basics: Covered
    </h2>
    <p>
      We've now covered some of the basic concepts behind practical machine learning. The 
      steps in teaching computers to understand data is actually quite simple: prepare some training
      data, choose a classifier, train the classifier and use cross-validation
      to verify how well the classifier is doing.
    </p>
    <p>
      The trickier bits are in understanding how features and classifiers can impact your results.
      Move on to the next tutorial by clicking the <em>Back</em> button below and choosing Tutorial 2.
    </p>
  </section>
</article>
