<article>
  <h1>Introduction to Machine Learning</h1>
  <summary>
    Machine learning is a burgeoning new technology for mining knowledge from
    data. But what is it all about? This tutorial will teach you some basics
    of applying machine learning through a simple example of prescribing contact lenses.
  </summary>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Computers are dumb...until we teach them things
    </h2>
    <p>
      So, what is machine learning?
    </p>
    <p>
      It boils down to a simple idea: teaching computers to see patterns in data.
      We see patterns in data all the time. If I show you a picture of a blimp,
      you'll recognize it as a blimp because you've seen blimps in the past and 
      you've learned that blimps are large, egg-shaped flying machines. At a lower 
      level, your brain is processing raw image data, allowing you to decide that 
      the blimp is in fact egg-shaped.
    </p>
    <p>
      Well, computers have none of this software built-in. Machine learning is
      all about training software to see data as blimps, cars, people, spoken words,
      stock prices, and almost anything else you can think of.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      The Basics
    </h2>
    <p>
      Alright, let's get our hands dirty and start using Protom on a real example:
      deciding what kind of contact lenses a person needs. On the right, you should
      be in the <em>Data</em> tab. From the <em>Choose data</em> menu, select <em>contact-lenses</em>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The machine learning setup is this: we have <em>training data</em>, which are examples
      of different classes we want to teach the computer about. Take a moment to look
      at the examples in the contact-lenses dataset. Here, we have 24 examples of 
      people and 3 classes: <em>soft</em>, <em>hard</em>, and <em>none</em>.
      <em>soft</em> means the person needs soft contact lenses, <em>hard</em> means
      they need hard lenses, and <em>none</em> means they don't need contact lenses.
    </p>
    <p>
      We teach the computer by training what is called a <em>classifier</em>. The classifier
      should then be able to classify examples by labeling them with the correct class.
      In this example, it decides whether a person needs soft, hard or no contact lenses.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Features
    </h2>
    <p>
      How do we train the classifier? Each example in the training data is actually a set of
      <em>features</em> that describe the example, and distinguish it from examples in other
      classes.
    </p>
    <p>
      Take for instance <em>Person 2</em>. She is young, has a myope prescription,
      doesn't have astigmatism and has a normal tear production rate. Other people have 
      different values for the same features. These features correlate in some way to what 
      kind of contact lenses are needed for each individual.
    </p>
    <p>
      During training, it is the classifier's job to learn this correlation. That way, when
      a new person comes into the optometrist's office, the classifier can decide what kind
      of contact lenses they need based on their age, prescription and health conditions.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Classifiers
    </h2>
    <p>
      In order to train the classifier, we must choose one first. Click on the <em>Classifier</em>
      tab at the top of the page. From the <em>Choose Classifier</em> menu, select
      <em>trees.J48</em>.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is a type of classifier called a decision tree, which learns a set of rules for 
      classifying examples based on feature values. How the tree works is outside the scope
      of this tutorial, but you can find a good description
      <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_tree">here</a>.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h2>
      Training and Testing
    </h2>
    <p>
      It's time to train the classifier. Click the <em>Training and Testing</em> tab. Click 
      <em>RUN</em>. Along with a summary of the trial's training data, features and classifier,
      <em>results</em> for this trial should appear on the page. For example, the accuracy
      is something like 83%.
    </p>
    <p>
      What do the results mean? How have we checked that the classifier worked? This is done 
      using <em>cross-validation</em>. The idea is to use 9/10 of the data for training, and the
      other 1/10 for testing. This is repeated 10 times (for each 'fold') and the results from
      each train-and-test are added up.
    </p>
    <p>
      The result is that each example is given to the decision tree at some point for classification.
      If the actual label doesn't match the classifier's decision, this is counted as an error.
      The accuracy means that 83% of the people were given the correct type of contact lenses.
    </p>
  </section>
</article>
